Guide to the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, Yale University, records
1905-2006
RU 41
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
22.25
(20 boxes)
The records consist of class materials and student papers from courses taught at the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies (School of Forestry prior to 1972) by Edward A. Bowers, Herman H. Chapman, B. E. Fernow, Henry Solon Graves, Gifford Pinchot, and Charles A. Walker. Also included are clippings, biographical notes, letters, publications, and photographs concerning the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies and its faculty; publications and talks of Carl E. Ostrom, Samuel J. Record and James W. Toumey; and records of Henry W. Hicock concerning alumni relations and his professional work.
Yale University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 24-A (YRG 24-A), Central records and records of the dean of the Yale School of Forestry.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Forestry and Environmental Studies Library, 1991-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of class materials and student papers from courses taught at the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies (School of Forestry prior to 1972) by Edward A. Bowers, Herman H. Chapman, B. E. Fernow, Henry Solon Graves, Gifford Pinchot, and Charles A. Walker. Also included are clippings, biographical notes, letters, publications, and photographs concerning the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies and its faculty; publications and talks of Carl E. Ostrom, Samuel J. Record and James W. Toumey; and records of Henry W. Hicock concerning alumni relations and his professional work.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forest conservation; Forest management; Forestry schools and education; Forests and forestry -- Research; Human ecology -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Bowers, Edward A. (Edward Augustus), 1857-1924; Chapman, Herman Haupt, 1874-1963; Fernow, B. E. (Bernhard Eduard), 1851-1923; Graves, Henry Solon, 1871-1951; Hicock, Henry W. (Henry Walter), 1891-1980; Ostrom, Carl E. (Carl Eric), 1912-; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Record, Samuel J. (Samuel James), 1881-1945; Toumey, James W. (James William), 1865-1932; Walker, Charles A. (Charles Allen), 1914-; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies; Yale University. School of Forestry
- Papers and records, circa 1905-1980; Accession 1991-A-079
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Class materials from courses at the Yale School of Forestry given or taken by E. A. Bowers, H. H. Chapman, B. E. Fernow, H. S. Graves, G. Pinchot.
    - Lumbering Notes by H. H. Chapman., 1904 (Box 1)
    - Methods of Estimating, notes on., 1912 (Box 1)
    - Yale Forestry School syllabus by Roy L. Marston. (Box 1)
    - Mayr, Heinrich. Paper on "Some fundamental principles of silviculture"., 1907? (Box 1)
    - Conifers plates (Box 1)
    - Dicotyledons plates (Box 1)
    - Pinchot, G. Lectures, 1911 (Box 1)
    - Maltby Tract, preliminary report on. (Box 1)
    - Silviculture, notes on. H. S. Graves., 1903 (Box 1)
    - Silviculture. B. E. Fernow. (Box 1)
    - History of Forestry I. H. H. Chapman., 1904 (Box 1)
    - History of Forestry II. H. H. Chapman., 1904 (Box 1)
    - Lumbering II. H. H. Chapman., 1904 (Box 1)
    - Forest law lectures. Bowers. (Box 1)
    - Valuation Surveys on Maltby Tract. (Box 1)
    - Working plan for Maltby Tract. (Box 1)
    - Management and details. Maltby, etc. (Box 1)
    - Methods of cruising., 1909 (Box 1)
  - Student papers and maps for Combined Sciences (87b) with Prof. Charles Walker, 1971-1980
    - Maps
      - New Haven, Wallingford, and Meriden (3 maps), 1967 (Box 1)
      - Quinnipiac River, New Haven and Fair Haven. (3 maps), 1868-1970 (Box 1)
      - The Eli Whitney Forest. (3 maps), 1929 (Box 1)
      - USGS: Collection Sites for Water Resources Data in the Quinnipiac River Basin (3 Copies), circa 1973 (Box 1)
      - USGS: Geologic Map of the Branford Quadrangle, Conn., 1962 (Box 1)
      - Map of Fair Haven Addresses and Map of Historic Development (Box 1)
      - Fair Haven NDP ECO-I Narrative and attachments submitted, 1974 June 4 (Box 1)
    - Papers
      - Reconstruction of the Grand Avenue Bridge, Preliminary Report. Prepared by Charles A. Maguire and Associates, Engineers., 1968 (Box 1)
      - Report of the Structural Condition of Existing Grand Avenue Bridge over the Quinnipiac River. Prepared by Charles A. Macguire and Associates Inc., 1970 (Box 1)
      - Ferguson, Bill. Survey of Attitudes toward Environmental Problems in New Haven., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Potter, Janice. Industrial Location and Population Distribution., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Allenby, Braden R. Energy and Population Redistribution., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Ridland, Rob. Who's Responsible? Mill River Pollution Abatement., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Russell, Chad. Mill River Study Group, Report of the Economics Sub-group Part I., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Lewis, Scott. Mill River Study Group, Report of the Economics Sub-group Part II., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Prechac, Yves. Pollution of the Mill River: A Chemical Survey., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Spivey, Robert A. The Mill River: A Perspective on Change., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Stowe, Larry. Proposed Treatment for the Mill River's Industrial Waste., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Freundlich, Larry. Mill River Study: The Law., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Brooks, David. Abstract of An Examination of Water Quality in the Mill River Watershed., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Hendrikson, Robert P. Ecology of the Mill River Marshlands, New Haven, CT., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Bissell, Bob. Part II: Picture-Essay of Mill River., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Aber, John. A History of the Mill River., 1971 (Box 1)
      - Hughes, Sandra L. An Analysis of the Canal Line Busway Proposal., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Hendrikson, Robert P. New Towns - A Proposal for Population Redistribution as a Function of Environmental Behavior Science., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Mills, V. A. Epidemiology and Toxicology of Air Pollution: A Study of the New Haven Problem., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Rogers, Thomas A. Air Pollution Levels and Socio-economic Class In New Haven., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Gravitz, Michael. A Brief Study of the Effectiveness of New Haven's Air Pollution Control Program, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Forrest, Terry A. New Haven's Air Shed. A multi-disciplinary assimilation., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Walzer, William. Planning for Improved Transportation Modes in New Haven, CT., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Kohlsaat, Thomas and Miller, David. Nitrogen and Phosphorus Pollution in the New Haven Harbor Watershed., 1972 (Box 1)
      - Bahr, Jean M. Industry Along the Quinnipiac., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Summary of Hydraulic Data for the Grand Avenue Bridge over the Quinnipiac River., 1973 (Box 1)
      - US Gsological Survey: Hydrogeologic Data for the Quinnipiac River Basin, CT. (2 copies)., 1973 (Box 1)
      - The Quinnipiac River and Water Quality., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Soils and Foundation Report, Grand Avenue Bridge Over Quinnipiac River, New Haven, CT., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Quinnipiac River Basin water quality survey data and map of sewage treatment plants and survey stations. (2 copies), 1973 (Box 1)
      - Riester, Carolyn. Some Coercive and Participative Aspects of Water Pollution Control Along the Quinnipiac River in Connecticut., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Fiebach, Nicholas. State Regulation of Water Pollution in Connecticut. The Phosphate Ban: A Case Study., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Ringel, Alan R. Public Health and the Quinnipiac: An Evaluation of Early Research., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Isaacs, Susan. Quinnipiac River: Water Quality Standards and Public Health Authority., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Aronoff, Andrew. Oil Pollution, New Haven Harbor, and State and U. S. Coast Guard Pollution Control Programs, An Overview., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Clark, Laurie. A History of the Oyster Industry in New Haven., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Sprenger, Craig. A General Discussion of the Effect of Water Quality on the Shellfish Industry of the Quinnipiac River and New Haven Harbor., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Meyer, Alden M. New Haven Harbor and Quinnipiac River: Plans for Pollution Control, Land Use, and Development., 1973 (Box 1)
      - Department of Environmental Protection, Hartford: Water Quality Standards., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Lawrence, John P. A Feasibility Study of a Total Energy System at Yale., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Memo re: Test results - Noise meter readings throughout the City of New Haven. To: [New Haven] Environmental Advisory Council, From: Jim O'Connor., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Porth, Richard J. Background Report on Fair Haven's Grand Avenue Bridge Proposal., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Krupp, Frederic D. The Grand Avenue Bridge and Impact on Air Quality. (2 Copies), 1974 (Box 1)
      - Porth, Richard J. New Haven's Dilemma Over Secondary Treatment of Sewage., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Environmental Analysis, RE: Proposed Replacement Facility - Calhoun Street Bridge, Delaware River Joint Toll Bridge Commission., 1974 (Box 1)
      - Isaacs, Susan J. Suspended Particulate Matter in the New Haven Area: An Evaluation of its Concentration and Particle Size Distribution with a Consideration of Meteorological Variables., 1974 (Box 1)
      - McDavid, Catherine. No Roller Skating...[an essay on New York City Parks.], 1974 (Box 2)
      - Williams, Paula J. The New Haven Water Company Lands: Their Value as Open Space., 1974 (Box 2)
      - Ferris, Gail A. Site Analysis for the New Haven Sewage Treatment Plants., 1974 (Box 2)
      - Ackerman, Stark. The Quinnipiac River; Water Quality and the Grand Avenue Bridge Project. (2 Copies), 1975 (Box 2)
      - Pieragostini, David. Legislation in Connecticut to Establish a Returnable Bottle System: A Review and Analysis., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Spungen, Elisa. An Overview of the New Haven Park System: Suggestions Toward Developing a Sociology of Parkland Use as a Means of Improving the System's Response to Societal Needs., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Jack, Wendy Ruther. Public Transportation to the Parks in the New Haven Area., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Sohn, Ruth. Reaction to a Bicycle Route Proposal: Four Interviews., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Becker, Lance D. Yes, But is it Safe? [an essay about bike routes], 1975 (Box 2)
      - Weyerhaeuser, Rick. Proposal for New Haven Bikeway., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Pieragostini, David. The Parks and Recreation Department: Administration., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Davidson. Diane. The History of Bikeway Proposals in the Greater New Haven Area., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Goldman, John A. An Exploration of a Possible New Haven Bike Route., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Moise, Laurene. Bicycle Transportation in Connecticut: State Plans for Bikeway Development., 1975 (Box 2)
      - Phillips, Susan P. Citizen Participation in Fair Haven., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Meeske, John. "Throughout its recorded history..." Quinnipiac River i n Fair Haven., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Kee, Gail. Federal, State and Local Water Pollution Control Legislation., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Walzer, William. Observation of the Quinnipiac River and its Salt Wedge., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Begley, Sharon. Overpackaging., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Rothman, Stephen. Crowding and Human Behavior., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Borzym, Jim Xerxes. Present Status and Developmental Possibilities for Long Island's Fresh Water Resources., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Kee, Gail. Calculating Insolation Received on Three Different Arrangements of Solar Panels., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Bergman, David et al. Solar Heating of Water for Becton Engineering Center: A Feasibility Study. (2 copies), 1976 (Box 2)
      - Borzym, Jim Xerxes. Class Project [on solar energy collection systems to heat water], 1976 (Box 2)
      - Rothrnan, Stephen. Utilizing Solar Energy at Becton Center., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Begley, Sharon. Solar Energy and Becton Center., 1976 (Box 2)
      - Racicot, Mark G. The Long Wharf Mudflat Ecosystem., 1980 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, biographical notes of faculty, historical papers, etc.
    - Photograph book (6"X 4"), collection of original photographs of people and places associated with YFS around 1906. Includes Milford, PA field camp. (Box 2)
    - Fieldbook: Field notes on surveying and mensuration. Summer 1912 on Pinchot Estate. Instructor Prof. Farnham, student Emanuel Fritz. (Box 2)
    - Autographs of famous foresters and lumbermen from Dean Graves, 1944. Includes many letters from U. S. lumber company owners and representatives.
      - Certificate of Henry S. Graves' election to American Association for the Advancement of Science. Signed by C. O. Howard sec., 1914 January 1 (Box 2)
      - Henry Solon Graves (Box 2)
      - A. Hadley, Pres. of Yale Univ., 1920 (Box 2)
      - James Wilson, Sec. USDA (Box 2)
      - R. M. Weyerhaeuser, 1908 (Box 2)
      - William Taft, 1913 (Box 2)
      - Wilbur L. Cross, 1911 (Box 2)
      - G. H. Meyers (Box 2)
      - A. Lawrence Lowell, Pres. Harvard Univ., 1914 (Box 2)
      - Harold C. Pekes. Federal Emergency Administrator of (Box 2)
      - Public Works, Washington. 1933 Appointed H. S. Graves to Mississippi Valley Committee of FEAPW. 1934 Announcement of H. S. Graves designation by the president to be a member of the Technical Subcommittee on Water Flow in the western Mississippi region. (Box 2)
      - F. E. Olrnsted, 1898 (Box 2)
      - W. L. Fisher, 1913. Secretary of the Interior. (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous letters and publications of H. S. Graves
      - Clippings
        - 1947 award to HSG (Box 2)
        - 1951 obituary (Box 2)
        - 1920 Resignation of HSG as Chief Forester (Box 2)
      - YSF summer school of forestry description by HSG (Box 2)
      - Graves' letter to Secretary of Agriculture stating intentions of resigning., 1920 February 25 (Box 2)
      - Letter to New Mexico Cattle Growers Assoc., 1920 April 12 (Box 2)
      - Photo of Barkhampsted, CT. (Box 2)
      - Book review of Forest Education by HSG. (Box 2)
      - Memorandum Regarding Forest Tract at Cumberland Gap. (Box 2)
      - "Ralph Clement Bryant 1877-1939", HSG. (Box 2)
      - "Public Welfare in Relation to Conservation of Natural Resources'', HSG., 1923 (Box 2)
      - "Remarks of HSG at the Dedication of the Toumey Road in Mohawk State Forest, Cornwall CT", 1935 (Box 2)
      - List of Papers and Reports by HSG, 1899-1941, compiled 1950 (Box 2)
    - Autographs - Yale Forestry School
      - List of autographed books in YFS library as of 16 Dec 1930. (Box 2)
      - Letter to Reynard de Sailly from HSG. (Box 2)
      - Letter from R. de Sailly, Inspecteur des Eaux et Forets, Paris, France. (Box 2)
      - Card of R. de Sailly. (Box 2)
      - Receipt from the Crystal Ice Co. for I. T. Woolsey Jr. (Box 2)
    - Diploma received by James William Toumey for PhD from the New York State College of Forestry at Syracuse University on 14 Jun 1920. (Box 2)
    - Copy of the newspaper of the American Forestry Congress (Box 2)
    - Record, S. J. (Dean of YSF 1945. Expert in wood structure properties)
      - Yale Alumni Fund News (2 copies), 1945 February, 1942 Apr, 1943 February (Box 2)
      - Synopsis of course by Prof. Toumey on Introduction to Forestry, 1900-1901 (Box 2)
      - "Reference - Extracts From" Author's Index and Subject Index. A list of papers and books on forestry., circa 1889-1930 (Box 2)
      - Tropical Woods. Number 82. Journal put out by YFS, established and edited by SJR. This issue is a tribute to SJR includes article by H. S. Graves, and a list of trees names after SJR., 1945 June 1 (Box 2)
      - "A Ciencia a Servico da Agricultura Americana. Heitor Grillo. Booklet 24 pp., 1940 (Box 2)
      - Obituaries for SJR. (Box 2)
      - Timber Topics Journal., 1944 January-February (Box 2)
      - New Haven Evening Register clipping. "1,400 canes donated to Yale", 1940 (Box 2)
    - Prof. Deubeis Plant Physiology Class: photo, negative, list of names., 1930 (Box 2)
    - Prof. Hawley's exams on Treatment of Woodland, 1918-1925 (Box 2)
  - Publications and Talks by Carl E. Ostrom
    - List of Publications by CEO (Box 2)
    - "Problem Analysis for a Program of Cooperative Research in Intensive Plantation Forestry i n India and the United States." CEO., 1974 (Box 2)
    - "Silvicultural Systems for the Major Forest Types of the United states." Agriculture Handbook No. 445. CEO wrote introduction., 1973 (Box 2)
    - "National Forest Management i n a Quality Environment: Timber Productivity". USDA Forest Service. Silviculture by CEO., 1970 (Box 2)
    - Series of articles on plant growth regulators, clearcutting, gum and resin flow, rural forestry systems, and shelterbelts and windbreaks. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous items from Yale Forestry School Alumni
    - Collection of letters to Henry W. Hicock, secretary of the YSF class of 1915, from members of that class. Includes address list of members from 1922. (Box 2)
    - Talks, papers and articles written by H. W. Hicock, 1909-1951. (Box 2)
      - "Glimpses of Connecticut Forests of the Past", 1909 January (Box 2)
      - North Colbrook - Phelps property, 1910 (Box 2)
      - "Charcoal Production.", 1948 (Box 2)
      - "Native versus Exotic Trees for Southern New England", 1949 August (Box 2)
      - "Native Trees and Ornamental Planting in Connecticut.", 1949 (Box 2)
      - "History of Forestry in Connecticut.", circa 1949 (Box 2)
      - Article on the treatment of fence posts with zinc chloride. (2 copies)., 1951 (Box 2)
      - Frontiers of Plant Science., 1951 November (Box 2)
    - Talks, papers and articles written by H. W. Hicock, 1956-1958
      - The Northeastern Logger. Contents includes HWH "Connecticut Forests - Asset or liability," and David M. Smith "Yale School of Forestry.", 1956 November (Box 2)
      - "Historical Background", 1957 March (Box 2)
      - Frontiers of Plant Science. (3 copies)., 1957 May (Box 2)
      - "The Suburban Forest", 1957 June (Box 2)
      - Frontiers of Plant Science., 1958 November (Box 2)
    - Talks, papers and articles written by H. W. Hicock, 1959-1971
      - Article on dedication of building at CAES to Bill Slate., 1959 April (Box 2)
      - "Hemlock Seedlings... Getting Them Off to a Good Start.", 1959 May (Box 2)
      - Connecticut's Forests: "Asset or Liability" (2 copies)., circa 1950s (Box 2)
      - "The Suburban Forest - Connecticut's New Frontier.", circa 1950s (Box 2)
      - "An Early History of Forests and Forestry in Connecticut", Connecticut Woodlands. (2 copies)., circa 1960 (Box 2)
      - Station News of the Connecticut Agriculture Experiment Station., 1963 July (Box 2)
      - Article in Cheshire Herald. "Forest Cover Description of Cheshire Park.", 1965 (Box 2)
      - "Cheshire's Roadside Trees". Includes map., 1971 (Box 2)
    - News Releases
      - Collection of newspaper clippings about H. W. Hicock retirement from head of forestry at the Connecticut Agriculture Experiment Station., 1959 (Box 2)
      - Article on Charcoal Production in CT. by HWH. (Box 2)
      - "Station Ecological Studies Call for Sweat and Theory." Bruce B. Miller., 1968 (Box 2)
    - Personal records of H. W. Hicock
      - Letters of appointment to Faculty of Yale Univ., 1946-1964 (Box 2)
      - Photo of the Senior personnel at CT. Ag. Exper. Sta., circa 1958-1960 (Box 2)
      - List of CAES bulletins and circulars written by HWH. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence H. W. Hicock
      - Correspondence mainly between Henry Hicock and Conn. Agric. Expt. Sta. regarding his employment, blister rust control work, and state forests., 1915-1926, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Yale Forestry School exams, schedules, special events from 1900-1909
      - Program descriptions (Box 3)
      - Entrance exam (Box 3)
      - USDA 1905 announcement of change of administration over forest reserves from U. S. Dept of Interior to USDA. (Box 3)
      - YFS receipt of Pinchot Estate for research center. (Box 3)
    - Yale Forestry School 1920-1926 collected by H. H. Chapman.
      - Dedication of Sage Hall (Box 3)
      - Schedules and exams (Box 3)
      - Guide to Maltby Tract (Box 3)
      - Letters to alumni (Box 3)
      - Letters to incoming students (Box 3)
      - Closing exercises (Box 3)
    - Senior Examinations, 1905-1918 (Box 4)
    - Junior Exams, 1918-1925 (Box 4)
    - Senior Examinations, 1921-1927 (Box 5)
    - Exams, schedules, and announcements collected by H. H. Chapman, 1909-1920 (Box 5)
    - Western Forestry Practices
      - Scrapbook with captions and photographs of people, forestry practices, and forest reserves in Colorado and Arizona. (Box 6)
      - Yale Forest School, prepared by Waldo D. Barbour class of 1911. Birch bark covered book (14"X 12") of photos from 1909-12. Photos present detailed documentation of the people and places associated with the Yale Forest School field camps in Milford, PA, Trinity, TX, Mount Carrnel, CT. Includes photographs of sawmills, skidder, and other tools and machinery used at that time. (Box 6a)
      - Loose photographs, undated (Box 6b)
    - Spring Field Work, Yale Forest School 1907-1918. Titles and photographs of people and places at field camps in Spring Valley, Missouri; Woodbridge Ala.; Doucette, Texas; Clarks, LA; Arkansas; Trinity, TX. Examples of turpentining, sawmills. 14 loose negatives. (Box 7)
- Publicity materials commemorating the school's centennial, 1999-2001; Accession 2003-A-084 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  No inventory available.